<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Christopher A. Searcy | Caitlin C. Mothes</title>
    <link>/authors/christopher-a.-searcy/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/christopher-a.-searcy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Christopher A. Searcy</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Caitlin C. Mothes</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Christopher A. Searcy</title>
      <link>/authors/christopher-a.-searcy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amphibian responses to livestock use of wetlands: new empirical data and a global review</title>
      <link>/amphibian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/amphibian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pastureland currently occupies 26% of Earth’s ice-free land surface. As the global
human population continues to increase and developing countries consume more proteinrich
diets, the amount of land devoted to livestock grazing will only continue to rise. To
mitigate the loss of global biodiversity as a consequence of the ever-expanding amount of land
converted from native habitat into pastureland for livestock grazing, an understanding of how
livestock impact wildlife is critical. While previous reviews have examined the impact of livestock
on a wide variety of taxa, there have been no reviews examining how global livestock
grazing affects amphibians. We conducted both an empirical study in south-central Florida
examining the impact of cattle on amphibian communities and a quantitative literature review
of similar studies on five continents. Our empirical study analyzed amphibian community
responses to cattle as both a binary (presence/absence) variable, and as a continuous variable
based on cow pie density. Across all analyses, we were unable to find any evidence that cattle
affected the amphibian community at our study site. The literature review returned 46 papers
that met our criteria for inclusion. Of these studies, 15 found positive effects of livestock on
amphibians, 21 found neutral/mixed effects, and 10 found negative effects. Our quantitative
analysis of these data indicates that amphibian species that historically occurred in closedcanopy
habitats are generally negatively affected by livestock presence. In contrast, opencanopy
amphibians are likely to experience positive effects from the presence of livestock, and
these positive effects are most likely to occur in locations with cooler climates and/or greater
precipitation seasonality. Collectively, our empirical work and literature review demonstrate
that under the correct conditions well-managed rangelands are able to support diverse assemblages
of amphibians. These rangeland ecosystems may play a critical role in protecting future
amphibian biodiversity by serving as an “off-reserve” system to supplement the biodiversity
conserved within traditional protected areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;fig-3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 3&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;FIG. 3. Locations of the reviewed studies examining the impacts of livestock grazing on amphibian abundance and richness. Of the 47 studies, 28 were conducted in the United States and 7 were conducted in Europe.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;fig-4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 4&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;FIG. 4. Strip plot displaying amphibian species’ response to livestock. Amphibians that prefer closed-canopy habitat are more negatively affected by livestock than are amphibians that prefer open-canopy or mixed habitats types. Each white, red, or blue circle represents an amphibian species; black circles are means for each habitat type.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of standardized methods to improve extinction risk classification</title>
      <link>/standardized_methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/standardized_methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standardized classification methods based on quantifiable risk metrics are critical for evaluating extinction threats because they increase objectivity, consistency, and transparency of listing decisions. Yet, in the United States, neither federal nor state agencies use standardized methods for listing species for legal protection, which could put listing decisions at odds with the magnitude of the risk. We used a recently developed set of quantitative risk metrics for California herpetofauna as a case study to highlight discrepancies in listing decisions made without standardized methods. We also combined such quantitative metrics with classification tree analysis to attempt to increase the transparency of previous listing decisions by identifying the criteria that had inherently been given the most weight. Federally listed herpetofauna in California scored significantly higher on the risk‐metric spectrum than those not federally listed, whereas state‐listed species did not score any higher than species that were not state listed. Based on classification trees, state endemism was the most important predictor of listing status at the state level and distribution trend (decline in a species’ range size) and population trend (decline in a species’ abundance at localized sites) were the most important predictors at the federal level. Our results emphasize the need for governing bodies to adopt standardized methods for assessing conservation risk that are based on quantitative criteria. Such methods allow decision makers to identify criteria inherently given the most weight in determining listing status, thus increasing the transparency of previous listing decisions, and produce an unbiased comparison of conservation threat across all species to promote consistency, efficiency, and effectiveness of the listing process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;fig-1-bg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 1&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 1. (a) Risk scores for California reptile and amphibian state-listed species and species of special concern priority 1, 2, and 3. (different letters denote significant differences between individual categories; overall stateand nonstate-listed species did not differ significantly [p = 0.34]) and (b) individual risk scores for all species assessed (∗, federally listed species, which scored significantly higher than nonfederally listed species [p &amp;lt; 0.001]).&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;fig-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 2&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 2. Classification trees describing listed versus unlisted reptile and amphibian species at the (a) state (California) and (b) federal level (misclassification rates [MC] in parentheses for each terminal node; numbers on branches, species’ risk scores for risk metric indicated) and (c) relative importance of each risk metric inherent in the state and federal listing process.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating ecological niche model accuracy in predicting biotic invasions using South Florida&#39;s exotic lizard community</title>
      <link>/lizard_niche/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/lizard_niche/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt; : Predicting environmentally suitable areas for non‐native species is an important step in managing biotic invasions, and ecological niche models are commonly used to accomplish this task. Depending on these models to enact appropriate management plans assumes their accuracy, but most niche model studies do not provide validation for their model outputs. South Florida hosts the world&amp;rsquo;s most globally diverse non‐native lizard community, providing a unique opportunity to evaluate the predictive ability of niche models by comparing model predictions to observed patterns of distribution, abundance and physiology in established non‐native populations.&lt;br&gt; 
&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Florida, USA.&lt;br&gt; 
&lt;strong&gt;Taxon&lt;/strong&gt;: Lizards.&lt;br&gt; 
&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt; : Using Maxent, we developed niche models for all 29 non‐native lizard species with established populations in Miami‐Dade County, Florida, using native range data to predict habitat suitability in the invaded range. We then used independently collected field data on abundance, geographical spread and thermal tolerances of the non‐native populations to evaluate Maxent&amp;rsquo;s ability to make predictions in both geographical and environmental space in the non‐native range.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt; : Maxent performed well in predicting across geographical space where these non‐native lizards were most likely to occur, but within a given geographical extent was unable to predict which individual species would be the most abundant or widespread. Comparisons with physiological data also revealed an imperfect fit, but without any consistent biases.&lt;br&gt; 
&lt;strong&gt;Main conclusions&lt;/strong&gt; : We performed one of the most extensive field validations of Maxent&amp;rsquo;s ability to predict where invasions are likely to occur, and our results support its continued use in this role. However, the program was unable to predict the relative abundance and geographical spread of established species, indicating limited utility for identifying which invasive species will be the greatest management concern. These results underscore the importance of other factors, such as time since introduction, dispersal ability and biotic interactions in determining the relative success of non‐native species post‐establishment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-and-code-found-at-httpsgithubcomccmothesnichemodel&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data and Code found at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ccmothes/NicheModel&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ccmothes/NicheModel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;fig-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Figure 1&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fig. 1: Predicted habitat suitability averaged across all 29 non‐native lizard species established in Miami‐Dade County. Black circles represent the number of recorded non‐native lizard localities within each Florida county. There was a strong positive correlation between the predicted and observed distributions of these nonnative lizards (p = 1e‐10)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
